Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף, Daf, the penultimate דף Daf
of שקלים, Shekalim, כ"א. Chaf-Aleph. We begin with the bottom of כ'
עמוד ב'. Chaf-Amud-Bet.
And because the משנה Mishna discussed who brings the קרבן Korban of
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol once he's dead to ensure that it
was brought, we have been getting into various aspects of the קרבן
Korban of the מנחה Mincha the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring,
the עשירית האיפה, Asirit Ha'Eifa, half in the morning and half in
the afternoon. So now the גמרא Gemara talks about how it's made
and we pick up where it says like this:
תופיני. Tufinei.
We're discussing a posthumous קרבן. Korban.
No, wait, the משנה Mishna was discussing the posthumous קרבן, Korban, that
leads the גמרא Gemara to discussing other aspects of how this קרבן,
Korban, how this מנחה Mincha was brought on a regular basis. Okay,
we'll get back to how it's brought in the special cases, but
now we're even just talking how it's regularly brought. So if you
take a look at it's about two-fifths from the bottom, the line
starts with the word,
there's actually a marginal note where it says לרוחכה Lerachecha or לרוחכה,
Lerachaka, so it starts with the word חמים. Chamim. חמים לרוחה, Chamim
Lerucha, חמים לרוחכה Chamim Lerachecha and then it says תופיני. Tufinei. Some
people see that, it's like near an asterisk at the beginning of
a line. Okay, now what is this מנחה?
Mincha? What is it? Like a regular מנחה? Mincha?
Yes, it's like a regular מנחה, Mincha, except that it's all burnt
up like a normal מנחה Mincha of a כהן, Kohen, which is
all burnt up. Okay, so the פסוק Pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra says,
I'll just read you the פסוק Pasuk so you know even what
we're talking about. Okay,
וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר
יקריבו לה'
ביום המשח
אתו.
Vayedaber Hashem el Moshe lemor: Zeh Korban
Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem beyom himashach
oto. So first of all, that's where we get the idea that
this is brought by every כהן Kohen on the day that they
begin their service. עשירית האיפה סלת תמיד מחציתה בבקר ומחציתה בערב. Asirit
ha-eifa solet tamid machatzitah va-voker u-machatzitah ba-arev.
Half in the morning, half in the afternoon.
על מחבת בשמן תעשה, Al machavat ba-shemen te'aseh, on a frying pan
with oil, מרבכת תביאנה, Murbachet tivienah, which also means, how do they
translate מרבכת? Murbachet? Repeatedly
baked. תופיני מנחת פתים. Tufinei minchat pitim.
Now the word תופיני Tufinei could mean broken into pieces like פתים,
Pitim, but we're going to see that the גמרא Gemara understands the
word תופיני Tufinei from the word אפיה. Afiya. So it both is
fried and it is baked. תקריב ריח ניחח לה'. Takriv reiach nichoach
l'Hashem. And the last פסוק Pasuk says: והכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו יעשה
אתה חק עולם לה' כליל תקטר. Ve-ha-kohen ha-mashiach tachtav mi-banav ya-aseh otah
chok olam l'Hashem kalil toktar. That the כהן המשיח, Kohen HaMashiach, the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings it, and that's how we learn that
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings it every single day. So it's
מחציתה, Machatzita, it's split in half, it's a type of a מנחה,
Mincha, it's brought when they are initiated into the service as we
learned yesterday, and now we're going to talk about how it is
made. So let's take a look. תופיני, Tufinei, okay, so baked is
how it's reading it. So it says: רבי
יוסי בשם רבי חנינא: Rabbi Yosi b'shem Rabbi Chanina: מטגנה ואחר כך
אופה אותה. Metagnah v'achar kach ofah otah.
First you sauté it, first you fry it and then you bake
it. רבי
אחא בשם רבי חנינא אומר: Rabbi Acha b'shem Rabbi Chanina omer: אופה
ואחר כך מטגנה. Ofah v'achar kach metagnah.
No,
you reversed it, first you bake it and then you fry it.
תופיני, Tufinei, now we're going to have a play on the words
of תופיני. Tufinei. What is תופיני? Tufinei? So תופיני תאפנה נא. Tufinei:
te'afena na.
So one explanation is you should bake it while it is נא.
Na. Now we normally translate נא Na as raw, but the גמרא
Gemara elsewhere, at least the בבלי, Bavli, translates נא Na as like
half-baked, not fully baked. So this is going to be understood to
correspond to the position that you fry it and then you bake
it, that when you bake it, it's already a little bit baked.
So תופיני נא, Tufinei na, bake it while it is half-raw.
So does this mean like don't bake it fully?
No, that's not how it's being understood. רבי אומר: Rabbi omer: תאפנה
נאה. Te'afena na'eh.
You should bake it that it looks nice. Now again, if you
look at the side there are all these different גרסאות, Girsa'ot, so
רכה, Raka, very softly. We'll read it that way: נאה. Na'eh. רבי
דוסא אומר: Rabbi Dosa omer: תאפנה רבה, Te'afena riba,
so many times. So you know, again there's other גרסאות Girsa'ot on
the side which is like נויה. Noya. Anyway,
but the way that with our גרסא Girsa it's read is bake
it many times. Okay, which means like according to some it means
bake it, then fry it, then bake it again. Okay, so we're
going to sort of bracket the many times and we're going to
look at the first two positions and try to link them to
the two positions we just said. Okay, so אתיין אילין פלוגתא כהני
פלוגוותא. Atyan ilayn pelugta kehani pelugvata. This debate links to that debate,
goes like the same issue of the debate about whether you fry
it first or bake it first. מאן דאמר תאפנה נאה, Man d'amar
ta'afena naeh,
again there's many גרסאות, Girsa'ot, we'll go with the one printed, the
one that says bake it nicely, כמאן דאמר k'man d'amar אופה ואחר
כך מטגנה. ofah v'achar kach metagnah.
So the way that the baking is nice is if you want
to make it... look nice when it's baked, you don't start by
frying it first, you bake it first, okay? Then whatever you do
afterwards you'll do afterwards so that when it's baked it still looks
very nice. מאן דאמר Man d'amar תאפנה נאה, te'afena na'eh, the one
that says you bake it when it's quasi-raw but not fully raw,
כמאן דאמר מטגנה ואחר כך אופאה. keman d'amar metagnah ve'achar kach ofah.
So that says first you fry it and then you bake it,
so when you get to the baking it is it is not
totally raw, it's quasi-raw. Okay. So anyway, different debates about what order
you did it and a play on the word of תופיני. tufinei.
Now, לא סוף דבר שמת, lo sof davar shemet, אלא אפילו נטמא
ואפילו נדחה ממום. ela afilu nitma ve'afilu nidcha mimum.
Now this gets back to the משנה, Mishnah, which is now we're
back to the special case, that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies
and the assumption that even when there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
it gets brought in his absence by his heirs or by communal
funds, okay, which is an interesting assumption. And now the גמרא Gemara
says, not even if he's not dead. Even if there's another reason
why he can't bring it, for example, what would be another reason?
He's טמא! tamei! Or maybe even if he has a מום. mum.
Now that's also interesting because normally a טמא tamei person can have
a קרבן korban brought for them. So this assumes that he is
not only having it brought for him, he is actually the one
that is bringing it, okay? And the פסוק pasuk says והכהן המשיח
תחתיו יעשה אותה, vehakohen hamashiach tachtav ya'aseh otah, he does it, okay?
So question's really if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was every single
day in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash bringing this קרבן, korban, but
nevertheless the מנחה, Mincha, the גמרא Gemara here assumes that at least
he has to be fit to be to have it brought. What
happens if he is טמא tamei or if it's a מום? mum?
And it would presumably then fall into the same rule as our
משנה, Mishnah, it would be brought from other funds although you wouldn't
have the heirs pay for it if he's alive and he's just
טמא. tamei. So again one wonders, does that mean it would be
brought in his absence but from his funds? Okay, not so clear.
לא סוף דבר שמת, Lo sof davar shemet,
meaning like not only, it doesn't end the matter, it's not only
in a case when he dies, okay? That's not the end of
the discussion. Even in these other cases also it would be brought
for him.
And even if he's there every day?
Well, assuming that he actually personally brought it, yes.
Right, right, but then if it was brought, I'm sorry, he didn't
have to pay
for it and have somebody else? That's what I said, not clear.
It would be bizarre to think his heirs would pay for it
if he's טמא. tamei.
No, but just it happens like his rent?
Why not his own, why not just take it, why not just
have him pay for it?
No, right, that's what I'm saying, meaning like somebody else brings it
for him and he pays for it?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's what I'm saying, it's not clear from this
what it means. It means it was brought for him but whether
who's paying for it you would assume that he would ultimately have
to pay it, yeah, I agree.
Wouldn't another כהן kohen right away take his place? We have that,
yes. Yes, like the woman with the seven sons, right? On him
and then take cause one was טמא, tamei, the other took over.
Right, if he's needed. Well, right, but if he's if he's needed,
you know like you got that on יום כיפור Yom Kippur where
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol becomes טמא tamei and you ממנים אחר
תחתיו. memanim acher tachtav. But that's when he's needed. Like if he's
not needed that day in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and he
happens to be טמא, tamei, and like what, every time he becomes
טמא tamei he has to go ahead, you have to appoint another
כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? I mean, no. If he's needed then you
appoint somebody else in his place.
And he's constant, right?
Yeah, I mean the סגן, Sgan, right, can serve, right, if he's
needed somebody takes his place. But you don't you don't substitute him
just cause one day he's
טמא. tamei. Okay, so תני רב יהודה בן פזי דבר דליא, Tani
Rav Yehuda ben Pazi devar Dalya,
which is apparently his name, or a place from the place of
ברדליא, Bardalya, ואפילו נדחה ממום. ve'afilu nidcha mimum.
Okay, even if he's pushed out because of a מום, mum, again,
he can't bring, somebody would have it brought for him. מניין לכהן
גדול שמת ולא מינו אחר תחתיו? minayin leKohen Gadol shemet velo minu
acher tachtav? Now we get to the basic הלכה halacha about how
do we know that it's brought for him when he's not around?
Okay, whether again, you know, and where do we get this idea?
Maybe if he can't bring it, maybe certainly if he's not alive,
you know, it's one thing to be alive and not be present
and it's brought for him, but how do we know it's brought
even after he's dead? מניין שמת ולא מינו אחר תחתיו שתהא מנחתו
קריבה משל יורשין? minayin shemet velo minu acher tachtav shetehe minchato keriva
mishel yorshin? How do you know you bring it? Two questions really.
A, how do you know you bring it after he's dead? B,
how do you know it comes from the estate? תלמוד לומר מבניו
יעשה אותה. Talmud lomar mibanav ya'aseh otah. So
it's a play on the פסוק pasuk that the פסוק pasuk says
הכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו, hakohen hamashiach tachtav mibanav, that
the כהן kohen that becomes anointed into you know, from the son
of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, meaning that the new כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol will bring it, but we cut the פסוק pasuk in
half and we only read the words מבניו. mibanav. מבניו יעשה אותה.
mibanav ya'aseh otah. Not that he's anointed from the sons of the
of the ex-כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, of the previous כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. No, we just need מבניו יעשה אותה. mibanav ya'aseh otah. The
sons of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol bring it. When would the
sons bring it? Must be he's dead. מבניו יעשה אותה. Mibanav ya'aseh
otah. יכול יביאנה לחצאין? yachol yevienah lachatza'in?
Maybe when it's brought by the sons, he's dead, maybe it is
brought like when he brings it, half in the morning, half in
the afternoon? תלמוד לומר אותה. Talmud lomar otah. יעשה אותה. ya'aseh otah.
So in that last פסוק pasuk where it speaks about the you
know, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings it, it doesn't mention the
half and half. So since we're reading that פסוק pasuk to talk
about that he's dead, then we read, oh, when he's dead and
the sons bring it, they bring it whole. They don't bring it
in two halves. כולה אמרתי. Kulah amarti. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. So he's supposed to bring it all as one?
He's supposed to
bring half in the morn- no, no, they bring it all as
one. That's what the משנה Mishna says that when they bring it—well,
the גמרא Gemara is going to say—well, no, no, when he, every
day that he's not around and there's no כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
the מנחה mincha continues to be brought, it comes from the—from the
estate, from the heirs, and it's brought as a whole unit, not
as half units. The גמרא Gemara in a minute will discuss how
that—what implications that has of how it's brought. But that's in the
משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna says, משלו יורשין רבי יהודה אומר משלו
יורשין ושלמה הייתה קרבה. mishlo yorshin Rabbi Yehuda omer mishlo yorshin u'shleima
hayta k'reva. Okay, not in two halves. Okay, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון אומר אינה באה אלא משל ציבור. Rabbi Shimon
omer eina ba'ah ela mishel tzibur. It's coming from communal funds. שנאמר
חוק עולם, she'ne'emar chok olam, an eternal edict. That's how the פסוק
pasuk ends. חוק עולם לה' כליל תקטר. chok olam l'Hashem kalil tuktar.
So, חוק עולם. chok olam. So basically, now how does that say
it's from the ציבור? tzibur? So it says, מי שברית כרותה לו,
mi she'berit k'ruta lo, the one for whom it's a—like you make
the covenant for their sake. Again, so again, it's
somehow the—what's his name—the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah says—says the דרשה drasha
is the following: ממי שהעולם שלו, mimi she'ha'olam shelo, from the funds
of the one who is the עולם, olam, who is, you know,
who—who owns everything, God. From God's funds. So it's from God's funds,
it's from the communal funds that have been given to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and not from the יורשים. yorshim. I don't quite
get that. Neither do I. Okay. So, anyway, but somehow עולם olam
means God. So it's God's קרבן korban at this stage and therefore
comes from God's funds, from בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash funds. כליל תקטר,
kalil tuktar, כליל הקטרה. kalil haktara. You burn it all up. You
don't do it in two halves. So there's no debate about this
idea when he's dead you do it as a unit, you don't
do it in halves, but the debate is where does it come
from? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it comes from the יורשים. yorshim.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it comes from the ציבור. tzibur. Now
we've got a little problem because in our משנה, Mishna, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon said this is one of the תקנות, takanot, remember, that
בית דין Beit Din was מתקן metaken that it would come from
the ציבור. tzibur. But according to this, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
learning out from a פסוק pasuk that it comes from the ציבור.
tzibur. Is that a סתירה? stira? So which is it? Is it
a פסוק—okay, pasuk that's what the בבלי Bavli would say. Let's see
what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says. Is it a פסוק pasuk that it
comes from the ציבור tzibur or is it a תקנה? takana? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
The פסוק pasuk said it had to be חצי, chatzi, right? So
that was just under
normal circumstances, but the last פסוק pasuk which talks about the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and is read to also talk about when the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was dead, somehow they—that's read into the פסוק.
pasuk. There they emphasize that it's talking about whole, complete. Okay. רבי
אבא בר ממל בעי. Rabbi Abba bar Mamal ba'ei. רבי אבא בר
ממל Rabbi Abba bar Mamal asked. מחלפה שיטתיה דרבי שמעון. machlafa shitatei
de'Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is reversing his position. תמן אמר
משלו יורשין. taman amar mishlo yorshin. There he says it comes from
the יורשים. yorshim. Now where is there? So the מפרשים mefarshim say
it means implicit in the משנה Mishna because the משנה Mishna he
says it comes from communal funds as a תקנה. takana. So presumably
means that in principle it comes from the
יורשים. yorshim. והכא אמר, ve'hacha amar, here, in what we just quoted,
he says משל ציבור mishel tzibur that fundamentally it comes from communal
funds. אמר רבי חייא בר בא. amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ba. Now
by the way, it is an interesting conceptual question, right? Because if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is daily bringing a קרבן korban and
it does come from his funds, on the one hand it's a
personal קרבן. korban. On the other hand, why does he have an
obligation to bring a personal קרבן korban every single day? And obviously
it's because he also is the public figure and represents the entire
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So to some degree even though it's a
personal קרבן, korban, it's also a קרבן korban of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, you know, it's a קרבן korban that has to be
taking place in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And it's through the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol as the representative of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. So as such, when he is dead, the interesting question of
is it coming from the יורשים yorshim which emphasizes the personal nature
of the קרבן, korban, or is it coming from communal funds which
emphasizes the public nature of the קרבן korban is I think a
very fascinating question, you know, in terms of this dual dimension. Especially
when he's dead. When he's alive you could say the personal nature
is underscored—that he's alive, it's his קרבן, korban, so it's his funds.
But once he's dead and it still is brought, the more sort
of public aspect of it, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash aspect of
it should more dominate and therefore it would come משל ציבור. mishel
tzibur. So I think you can really hear that as a principled
position. Of course now the גמרא Gemara is saying, yeah, okay, that's
what you said now based on a פסוק, pasuk, but in the
משנה Mishna you made it sound like it was only a תקנה.
takana. So what is it according to you רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that it's coming משל ציבור? mishel tzibur? Is it a דאורייתא de'oraita
or is it a תקנה? takana? So let's see what the answer
is. אמר רבי חייא בר בא, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ba, ולא
יאות
הוא מקשה? v'lo ya'ut hu makshe? Is he—is he not asking well?
Again, it's always hard to know in the בבלי Bavli if it's
a statement or a question. Okay, which is suffice. So we don't
have an answer. Yeah, that's a good question. So what's the answer?
So אתא רבי יעקב בר אחא רבי אבוהו בשם רבי יוחנן, ata
Rabbi Yaakov bar Acha Rabbi Abbahu beshem Rabbi Yochanan, דבר תורה הוא
שתהא בא מן הציבור. dvar Torah hu she'tehe ba min ha'tzibur. Look,
it is—yes, it is biblically מן הציבור, min ha'tzibur, again, there's a
lot of parentheses, we're going to skip the parentheses. Biblically it's מן
הציבור min ha'tzibur like we quoted in the past פסוק. pasuk. But
what does it mean מן הציבור? min ha'tzibur? There's two possible ways
we could get it מן הציבור. min ha'tzibur. הייתי אומר יגבו לה.
hayiti omer yigbu lah. I would have said it comes מן הציבור,
min ha'tzibur, we have to do a special collection, a special fund
now, a special appeal. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is dead and
we need everybody to donate money that we're going to use to
bring his קרבן korban now that he's dead. So that would have
been the first stage. Meaning it wouldn't be covered by the מחצית
השקל. machatzit ha'shekel. Well, that's what he's going to understand is the
תקנה. takana. The fact that the משנה Mishna says it's a תקנה,
takana, שהתקינו שתהא בא מתרומת הלשכה, she'hitkinu she'tehe ba mi'trumat ha'lishka, that
you get it not from a special fund but you get it
from the תרומת הלשכה. trumat ha'lishka. תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishkah and again,
the difference is that the תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishkah was for קרבנות
ציבור, Korbanos Tzibbur, communal sacrifices. So it's a little bit different of
saying this is not a קרבן ציבור, Korban Tzibbur, it's the קרבן
Korban of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but the fee for it,
the payment for it comes from the ציבור. Tzibbur. So in principle
then we would have had to done a special special collection for
it. The תקנה Takanah was that we allow ourselves to take it
from the תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishkah funds which are for קרבן ציבור.
Korban Tzibbur. Okay, so it's communal funds but it's not a קרבן
ציבור Korban Tzibbur but the תקנה Takanah allowed us to take it
from those funds. All right, and again interesting about this dual nature
of the of the מנחה Minchah of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Now the גמרא Gemara asks these questions about it being brought whole,
what other implications they have. Michael, you'll enjoy this because I'm sure
these are all the questions that you would have asked. Okay, התקינו
שתהא He'tikinu she'te'hei now... רבי יוסי אמר רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yossi amar
Rebbe Yochanan בעיא Ba'ei מאי היא. Mai hi. Now the idea that
comes whole, how does that play out? שלמה בשחרית ושלמה בין הערביים,
Sheleimah b'shacharis u'sheleimah bein ha'arbayim, do you still keep the idea of
doing it in the morning and in the afternoon, except rather than
doing two halves, now you do two wholes, a whole in the
morning and a whole in the afternoon? Okay, or או O שלמה
בשחרית ובטלה בין הערביים, Sheleimah b'shacharis u'beteilah bein ha'arbayim, or do you
bring it whole in the morning and nothing in the afternoon? Very
reasonable question. So קא מיפשטא ליה Ka mifshta lei דכתיב d'chesiv or
now again, that was sort of... so he then sort of resolved
it for himself because it says מנחת תמיד. Minchas tamid. What does
כהא K'ha mean?
כהא K'ha or כאשר Ka'asher to... again, I'm not exactly sure again
exactly the sort of tense here, the grammar here, you know. The
קרבן נתנאל Korban Nesaneil says it sort of means אם תמצי לומר.
Im timtzi lomar. I don't know how you get קא מיפשטא ליה
Ka mifshta lei like if you if it is פשיטא Pshita to
you because of the following פסוק, Pasuk, then I have the next
follow-up question. So if you say that we can resolve that because
of a פסוק Pasuk of תמיד. Tamid. Now תמיד Tamid constantly, you
can't do something once in a morning and call it תמיד. Tamid.
If you think about the things that are תמיד, Tamid, קרבן תמיד
Korban Tamid is once in the morning once in the afternoon, right?
So and the you know the מנורה Menorah is תמיד, Tamid, you
know, but that's also through the night they have a question. קטורת
Ketores is תמיד Tamid and that's once in the morning once in
the afternoon. So תמיד Tamid is it has to be once in
the morning once in the afternoon. So yes, if that's what how
you resolve it and therefore it'll be שלמה Sheleimah in the morning,
whole in the morning and whole in the afternoon, here's my next
question. שלושה לוגין מה הן? Shlosha lugin mah hein? How about the
fact that with that oil that's an עשרון, Issaron, you bring three
לוג, Log, with that flour that עשרון Issaron you bring three לוג
Log of oil? We know that because of we're going to say
in a minute, when you bring a מנחת נסכים Minchas nesachim by
a sheep, so you bring an עשרון Issaron of סולת Soles and
you bring a quarter of a הין, Hin, a הין Hin is
12 לוג. Log. So you bring three לוג Log of oil, so
that's normally the proportion, one עשרון Issaron of סולת Soles with three
לוג Log of oil. Okay, so we know you normally bring three
לוג Log with it. Now in a normal when the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is alive, you bring half the עשרון Issaron and one
and a half לוג Log in the morning, half the עשרון Issaron
and one and a half לוג Log in the afternoon.
Now that we're bringing a full עשרון Issaron in the morning and
a full עשרון Issaron in the afternoon, what do we do with
the שמן? Shemen? Okay? So שלושה לוגין מה הן? Shlosha lugin mah
hein? שלושה לוגין שחרית ושלושה לוגין בין הערביים? Shlosha lugin shacharis u'shlosha
lugin bein ha'arbayim? Does that also get doubled? So three in the
morning, three in the afternoon? או לוג ומחצה שחרית ולוג ומחצה בין
הערביים? O log u'mechetza shacharis v'log u'mechetza bein ha'arbayim? No, we only
have the flour is the full unit in the morning and the
afternoon but the oil doesn't change, the oil is half in the
morning, half in the afternoon. Not exactly clear why it would say
that. אמר רבי חזקיה אף היא צריכא ליה, Amar Rebbe Chizkiyah af
hi tzericha lei, so even that was part of the question, you
know, okay. Now, שני קמצים מה הן? Shnei kematzim mah hein? Now
how about the קומץ? Komets? Because you would also bring with this,
again, not explicit but you would bring with this a קומץ Komets
of לבונה. Levonah. Like by a normal מנחה Minchah you would have
oil, flour, and the לבונה. Levonah. Now we there's a debate in
the גמרא Gemara whether with the מנחה Minchah of a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol you bring two קמצים Kematzim or one קומץ Komets of
לבונה. Levonah. Okay? So this is sort of assuming that you would
normally bring one קומץ Komets with each half. So that when you
did it in halves, half in the morning half in the afternoon,
each one would be one קומץ. Komets. So now our question is
now that you're bringing it as wholes, a whole in the morning,
a whole in the afternoon, what happens with the קומץ Komets of
the לבונה? Levonah? שני קמצים מה הן? Shnei kematzim mah hein? שני
קמצים שחרית ושני קמצים בין הערביים? Shnei kematzim shacharis u'shnei kematzim bein
ha'arbayim? Do you take the full amount of the לבונה Levonah that
you would normally do for, you know, the two and do two
in the morning and two in the afternoon? או קומץ אחת שחרית
וקומץ אחת בין הערביים? O kometz achas shacharis v'kometz achas bein ha'arbayim?
That no, you keep it as one in the morning, one in
the afternoon. Because basically by normally it would be everything would be
half... I'm gonna start by use my new whiteboard. Okay, so normally
you would have you know it would start like this, you'd have
one עשרון Issaron of flour, right? You'd have three לוג Log of
oil and this is our recipe, and two קמצים Kematzim of קטורת...
Ketores... what? לבונה? Levonah? Right, of לבונה, Levonah, right. Sorry, okay, of
לבונה. Levonah. So
so then you'd split it in half, so every in the morning
you'd have here's the morning here's the afternoon, you'd have half of
an עשרון Issaron of flour, right? One and a half one and
a half of oil, and one קומץ, Komets, right? And the same
here, right? Half עשרון, Issaron, one and a
half... So now that he said we're going to double that, and
we're going to make that one. So the question now is, now
that we've doubled that, do we keep everything else the same one
and a half, one and a half, one and one like we
normally would do, or do we now double everything else? Three and
three and two and two? Okay, so that's the question that's being
asked.
But I also have a הווא אמינא hava amina where we don't
do anything in the afternoon.
No, now if, that's like the אם תמצי לומר. im timtzi lomar.
If we decide that we're doing one שלם shalem in the morning
and one שלם shalem in the afternoon, are we now going to
double the rest of the things that came along with it? All
right, so let's take a look. So שני קמצים מהם? sheni kematzim
mehem?
שני קמצים בשחרית ושני קמצים בין הערביים? sheni kematzim b'shacharis v'sheni kematzim
bein ha'arbayim? So we're going to double it. או קומץ אחד בשחרית
וקומץ אחד בין הערביים? o kometz echad b'shacharis v'kometz echad bein ha'arbayim?
Or do we keep those things at their normal proportion, normal amount?
אמר רבי יוסי כולה למדו לקומץ ממנחת חוטא. Amar Rabi Yose kula
lamdu l'kometz miminchas chotei. Wait a minute. We learned the idea that
you bring a קומץ kometz of לבונה levona by this from the
case of the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of, and
where there's the קומץ kometz of לבונה. levona.
Now the next line is a little bit challenging. מה להלן שני
קמצים אף כאן שני קמצים. mah lehallan sheni kematzim af kan sheni
kematzim. The same way there it's two קמצים, kematzim, here it's two
קמצים. kematzim. Or sometimes it's not two קמצים. kematzim. There's one קומץ.
kometz. So exactly what that means and how we're resolving it, I
don't know. There's a lot of speculation on that. All right. אמר
רבי חזקיה כולה למדו שלושה לוגים מתמיד שבין הערביים. Amar Rabi Chizkiya
kula lamdu shlosha lugin mitamid shebein ha'arbayim. Where do you learn that
you bring three לוג? log? It's from a normal תמיד, tamid, a
normal קרבן korban that's a sheep, has a סולת soles of flour,
one עישרון issaron of flour, and three לוג. log. מה להלן שלושה
לוגים אף כאן שלושה לוגים. mah lehallan shlosha lugin af kan shlosha
lugin. So the same way there it's three לוג, log, here it's
three לוג. log. The only problem is there it's three לוג log
for every okay, one minute. ומה תמן צריכה ליה אף כאן צריכה
ליה. u'mah taman tzericha lei af kan tzericha lei. And the same
way there it's a question, here it's a question. What's the question
there is not clear. Again, the מפרשים meforshim have different speculation. But
the key the answer here at least seems to be that once
the basic way we learn out the three לוג, log, how do
we know three לוג? log? Because a normal מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim
for a sheep is one עישרון issaron of flour plus three לוג.
log. Okay, that's the normal מנחה, mincha, right, a רביעית ההין שמן.
revi'is ha'hin shemen.
So what he seems to be saying is once that's true, we
learn it out from the from the ratio here. We learn out
that each עישרון issaron gets three לוג. log. So once that's true,
once we've made this, we've doubled this and made this a full
עישרון, issaron, then this has to become three לוג log to go
along with it. That seems to be what they're saying about the
קומץ. kometz. The same way over here by a normal מנחת נסכים
minchas nesachim it's three לוג log for עישרון, issaron, here it's going
to be. Now here, why we assume two and two, that I
don't know, because by all other things it's one, it's one קומץ
kometz per per, you know, you know, that comes with the מנחה,
mincha, not two. So that's a so what the answer there is
is a lot less clear.
What happened to the answer that if you do the full thing
in the morning the afternoon is פטור? patur?
Right, we're dealing with the אם תמצי לומר. im timtzi lomar. On
the side that we do double it, okay, then how do you
deal with that?
Oh, I'm sorry, how much is a לוג log as far as
quantity?
A לוג log is about well when we have a for קידוש
kiddush what we call a רביעית revi'is is a רביעית revi'is of
a לוג log and that's about and that's about three and a
half ounces. So a לוג log is about fourteen ounces. Fourteen ounces?
Yeah, something like that.
So yeah, I find it interesting that he's spending more on the
at dacha than on a log.
That's a good point. Yeah, I don't know what to say about
that. All right, let's finish up this paragraph.
זה הכלל בשלנו יהא. Zeh haklal b'shelanu yehei.
Okay,
now this is that they allowed the כהנים, kohanim, again, one of
these things that בית דין Beis Din makes the rules, they allowed
the כהנים kohanim to use the wood and the and the salt
which is for the קרבנות korbanos for eating the meat that they
themselves then would would get from the קרבן korban for roasting that
meat and for putting salt on that meat. רבי שמעון נחמני בשם
רבי יונתן בדין היה שיהיו מועלים בהן. Rabi Shimon Nachmani beshem Rabi
Yonasan badin hayah sheyiheyu mo'alin bahen. Really, there should have been מעילה.
me'ila. והן גזרו שלא ימעלו בהן. vehen gazru shelo yim'alu bahen. And
they decided that there wouldn't be מעילה. me'ila. Okay, that's the רשות,
reshus, the תנאי בית דין. tnai Beis Din. Okay. Now this might
be going also on the case of the חטאת chatas which also
said that there's no חטאת chatas with the ashes of the פרה.
parah. But but anyway, I think the plural language is it's going
on the line by the כהנים. kohanim. But anyway, now we transition
into the idea of the ashes of the חטאת, chatas, the ashes
of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So they also said that those
ashes there's no מעילה. me'ila. So the גמרא Gemara says והתני ותני
ברייתא v'hatani v'tani baraisa חטאתי chatasi מלמד שמועלים בה. melamed shemo'alin bah.
Okay, so you that there is מעילה me'ila in the actual animal
that's the פרה אדומה parah adumah once it's sanctified, בה מועלים ואין
מועלים באפרה. bah mo'alin v'ein mo'alin b'afrah. You're מועל mo'el in it
but not in its ashes. חטאת היא, Chatas hi, it is like
a חטאת, chatas, not the ashes. So the point is why did
we need a תקנה takana to say there's no מעילה me'ila in
the ashes if we know from the פסוק pasuk there's no מעילה
me'ila in the ashes? All
right. אמר רבי אבוהו בראשונה, Amar Rabi Abbahu barishona, you know what?
You're right. Biblically there is no מעילה me'ila in the ashes.
ובראשונה היו משתקשקין בה. ubarishona hayu mishtakshakin bah. Okay, whatever that means,
the מפרשים meforshim say it means that they would use it as
we'll see in
the
next... They would use it for some type
of a medicinal purpose and they would put the ashes on their
wounds and presumably that would help in the healing. Okay, so basically
once you said that there was no מעילה, meila, people would really
like misuse it.
וגזרו שימעלו בו, Vegazru sheyima'alu bo, then they made rabbinic מעילה meila
because they had to get people to get their hands off the
ashes. But what happened? כיון שנגדרו, Kivan shenigderu, once they were sort
of separated themselves out, because now nobody wanted to be sprinkled with
the ashes of פרה אדומה Parah Adumah because everybody heard oh there's
מעילה, meila, that's pretty funny you know you would think okay מעילה
meila if you misuse it, but somehow that led to people being
treating it as too much taboo and not wanting to get sprinkled
with the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah ashes. So therefore גזרו שלא ימעלו
בו gazru shelo yima'alu bo so we went back to the original.
So it's similar to the answer before about the ציבור. tzibbur. Is
ציבור דאורייתא tzibbur de'oraisa or is the ציבור tzibbur fund תקנה? takana?
And the answer is both. So is no מעילה meila by the
ashes of פרה אדומה דאורייתא Parah Adumah de'oraisa or תקנה? takana? The
answer is both. There was an interim stage that we were then
sort of like reversing. Okay, but it does go back to דאורייתא.
de'oraisa. Stages reversed the גזירה. gezera.
Right. ועל הקינין Ve'al hakinim and the last תקנה takana is if
there are not enough birds the money something you bought it from
the supplier and there's now the birds died, or there were פסולות,
pesulos, then you would then you would replace them. And the question
was from what fund? Either from communal funds or it would be
the supplier's responsibility to replace it. So the גמרא Gemara says pretty
much it's a repeat of what we said before. האישה הזאת במה
היא מתכפרת, Ha'isha zos bamah hi miskaperes, which is really like explaining
why we made the תקנה. takana. If we did not replace the
birds, so the woman's going to assume her קרבן korban was brought
and she's going to assume she's טהורה, tehora, how is she being
atoned for if one of the birds you know was פסול pasul
or died and you don't have enough money for it? So you
need to find a way to replace it, either from communal funds
or the supplier. So אמר רבי יצחק: Amar Rabbi Yitzchak: תנאי בית
דין הוא tenai beis din hu המספק את הקינין הוא מספק את
הפסולות ואת האבודות. hamaspek es hakinim hu maspek es hapesulos ve'es ha'avudos.
The guy supplying the birds he has responsibility to replace any lost
or invalid birds.
Unless it was through negligence?
Presumably that's the deal you make by you know doing business with
the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. All right. הדרן עלך פרק מה שנמצא. Hadran
alach perek mah shemimtzo.
Okay. Entering into the, is this the last פרק? perek? Yes, to
the last פרק. perek. Okay.
משנה: Mishna: כל הרוקין הנמצאין בירושלים. kol harokim hanimtzo'in biYerushalayim. All spit
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, cause it's a very big question where the
spit came from. If it comes from a זב zav or זבה
zava then that spit is an אב הטומאה, av hatuma, okay, or
מצורע, metzora, whatever. So
כל הרוקין הנמצאין בירושלים kol harokim hanimtzo'in biYerushalayim all the
spit טהורין. tehorin. חוץ משוק העליון, chutz mishuk ha'elyon, except for the
one in the upper marketplace. There you have to assume that there's
a lot of טמאין tamei people walking around and we'll see why
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. דברי
רבי מאיר, Deivrei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yose omer: No, בשאר כל ימות השנה beshar
kol yemos hashanah really you can't be that lenient. In the normal
time of the year, not during the רגל, regel, שבאמצע shebe'emtza any
spit in the middle of the street is טמאין tmei'im because the
middle of the street is where everybody goes and the people aren't
you know if you're going where the masses are going you're not
being careful about טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah and there will be
זבים zavim and זבות zavos walking there. Now of course it's still
funny what percentage of the population is a זב zav and a
זבה, zava, but nevertheless it's a possibility and therefore you have to
be concerned that any spit in the middle of the road is
an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. שבצדדין, Shebetzadin, if it's off at the
sides of the road, טהורין. tehorin. Then it's tahor. Who goes at
the sides of the road? The people that don't want to be
with all the masses and we're going to assume that it has
to do with טהרה taharah not because of agoraphobia, is that what
agoraphobia is? Agoraphobia? Fear of outdoors?
Fear of crowds. Open space.
Oh what's fear of crowds?
Agoraphobia. Agoraphobia. Okay anyway, so we're going to assume it's not because
of agoraphobia but it's just because they want to avoid You know,
טומאה tumah concerns. So they're going to walk at the edges of
the roads.
So if any spit at the edge if a צנוע וטהור tzanua
v'tahor will walk at the edges of the roads, won't walk in
the center where all the masses are.
Or is it just the opposite, that people who were walking on
the side of the road
don't want, you
know, are טמא, tamei, they
want to מטמא metamei everyone else and go on the side? That
would be inclusive. That would be very nice. But no, you know,
most people during most of the year don't care if they're טמא
tamei or not, right? Unless until you have to go to the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, unless you're a כהן. Kohen. So most of
the population went in the middle of the road, whether they were
טמא tamei or not. And only those who
go on the side were the טהורים. tehorim. ובשעת הרגל, U'v'shas haregel,
but it gets reversed at the time of the רגל, regel, cause
there, everybody is טהור tahor and everybody wants to stay טהור tahor
cause they gotta go to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. שבאמצע טהורים
שבצדדין טמאים, She'ba'emtza tehorim, she'batziddin temeim, those on the sides would be
טמא tamei cause they would have to, as Michael says, they'd have
to be responsible of not making other people טמא tamei cause the
proportions, you know, the distribution of the population change. מפני שהמועטין מסתלקין
לצדדין, Mipnei she'hamu'atin mistalkin litziddin, the minority is the one that has
to go at the margin. Okay, that could obviously be used metaphorically,
I'm sure. כל הכלים הנמצאים בירושלים, Kol hakelim hanimtza'im bi'Yerushalayim, now, let's
say you find a vessel in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Can you assume it's
טהור tahor and use it for a קרבן korban or תרומה? terumah?
Or do you have to be concerned it might be טמא? tamei?
So if it is דרך ירידה לבית הטבילה טמאים. derech yeridah l'veis
hatvilah temeim. If it's in the road that goes down to the
מקוה, mikvah, then it's טמא tamei cause why is it in the
road going down to the מקוה? mikvah? Somebody was bringing it there
to טובל tovel it. Okay. ודרך עליה טהורים, U'derech aliyah tehorim, then
on the road leaving the מקוה, mikvah, it's interesting, like it's like
what was- who- it's like Tevye, one staircase just going up and
the other just going down? So
apparently one road just goes down and the other road goes up
from the מקוה. mikvah. But maybe it's a one-way street, which side
of the street, or somehow it's obvious, it's obvious that it rolled
down, but of course even if you dropped it going up, it
was- I heard
for the מקוה mikvah at the- excavated- they have a little wall
right in the middle of the stairways.
What, for people going one way and the other? Really? Fascinating.
Just the concept of going to and coming from. Yeah, yeah.
ובשעת הרגל,
U'v'shas haregel,
when is that?
ערבי יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov, יום טוב? Yom Tov? That's come
up- yeah, yeah, that's a good question. I don't know, I don't
know. Okay. ודרך עליה טהורין, V'derech aliyah tehorin, and if they're on
the up way going
out it's- שלא כירידתן עליתן דברי רבי מאיר, she'lo k'yeridatan aliyatan divrei
Rabbi Meir, cause not going down is like coming up, if it's
coming up you assume it's- and of course it doesn't tell you
at all what you do with things that are not in the
environs of the מקוה, mikvah, right? That's very helpful if they're in
the environs of a מקוה. mikvah. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer,
Rabbi Yosei says, כולם טהורין, kulam tehorin, all vessels can be assumed
to be טהור. tahor. Interesting. Okay, the same Rabbi Yosei who said
that the major- right, it's like a reverse position. Rabbi Meir assumed
that most of the spit is okay, it's just it's in this
one place where the טמאים temeim people gather. And Rabbi Yosei says,
no, the טמאים temeim people are in all the middle of the
street. So presumably in the first part Rabbi Yosei felt that there
was more of a presence of טמאים, temeim, like really in the
communal spaces. And now they're reversing, that Rabbi Meir is more limited
in his assumption about which כלים kelim are טהור, tahor, and Rabbi
Yosei says כולם טהורין, kulam tehorin, no, we can assume all the
כלים kelim are טהור. tahor. So I really don't get how that,
you know, exactly how those positions sync. חוץ מן הסל והמגריפה והמריצה
המיוחדין לקברות, Chutz min hasal vehamagrefah vehamaritza hamyuchadin likvaros,
except for a basket and a shovel and a מריצה maritza is
also some type of like a pushing implement that they would use
in digging of
graves. And- so those types of things obviously are assumed to be
טמא. tamei. But everything else is assumed to be טהור. tahor. So
again it's quite fascinating. He recognizes that there are טמאים temeim people
in society and we have to assume spit is from the טמאים
temeim people, but vessels, you know, maybe it's like a כל דפריש
מרובא פריש, kol d'parish meruba parish, that most of the people are
טהור. tahor. But then why are you concerned about the spit? So
I don't know, is the same Rabbi Yosei that's concerned about the
spit is okay with the vessels?
Now,
סכין שנמצאת בי"ד, Sakin shenimtzes b'yud-dalet, let's say you find a knife
on the fourteenth of ניסן. Nissan. So what are people using knives
on the fourteenth of ניסן? Nissan? שוחט shocheit the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So there, even if normally you're concerned that a vessel might
be
טמא, tamei, nevertheless if you find a knife on the fourteenth of
ניסן, Nissan, שוחט מיד, shocheit miyad, you can use it immediately and
you do not have to worry about- or maybe, but you don't
have to take it to the מקוה, mikvah, okay, you can assume
that it's וודאי vaddai has been taken to the מקוה. mikvah. Now
why don't you have to be concerned that maybe the owner was
going to take it to the מקוה mikvah later today? Because if
he took the knife to the מקוה mikvah later today, it would
not be able to be used until tonight, you need הערב שמש.
ha'arev shemesh. So therefore any knife that anyone would want to use
on the fourteenth would have had to have been taken to the
מקוה mikvah on the thirteenth and be טהור. tahor. So you can
assume if you find it on the fourteenth it's already טהור tahor
and you can use it
immediately. Okay, now, בי"ג, b'yud-gimmel, but if you find it on the
thirteenth, שונה ומטביל, shoneh umatbil, you have to go again- put it
in the מקוה. mikvah. Now you don't know it's again, but the
point is, if it's on the thirteenth, it might be that the
owner was planning on taking it to the מקוה mikvah later today,
right? And he could have taken it later today. and still used
it tomorrow on the 14th. So you don't know that it's been
to the מקוה mikvah yet, so you would have to take it
to the מקוה mikvah today if you wanted to. Now again, why
that's necessary given that רבי יוסי Reb Yose just said all כלים
kelim are טהור tahor is not clear. Maybe this is רבי מאיר,
Reb Meir, maybe we're being more strict because of קרבנות. korbanot. Okay,
let's take a look. Although why else would I care that it's
טהור tahor if not because of קרבנות? korbanot? Anyway, קופיץ. kofitz. Now
how about if you have a קופיץ kofitz which is more of
a cleaver than it is a שחיטה shechitah knife? So that, they
would not really use for שחיטה. shechitah. What you would use it
for is for dismembering a קרבן, korban, except there's for one קרבן
korban you would not want to use it for dismembering, which would
be the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach where it says כל עצם לא
ישברו בו. kol etzem lo yishberu bo. So therefore, this type of
a cleaver is something that they might need on the רגל regel
itself, on the 15th itself for the various קרבנות, korbanot, but they
would not need on the night, on the night of the 14th.
So this one they could, or on the day of the 14th.
So a cleaver, they could take to the מקוה mikvah on the
14th even if it would only, and that would be okay because
then they wouldn't need it until the 15th, so you would have
the הערב שמש ha'arev shemesh at the night. All right, now if
that's true, if you find it on the 14th, you don't know
if this is before or after it's been to the מקוה. mikvah.
Okay, cause this is, is that clear? Meaning the cleaver, the knife
you need on the 14th, so it had to be taken to
the מקוה mikvah on the 13th. So cleaver on the 15th, if
that's taken on the 14th, if you find it on the 14th,
you don't know what state it's in. Okay, so קופיץ kofitz בזה
ובזה, baze u'vaze, whether the 13th or the 14th, שונה ומטביל, shoneh
u'matbil, you have to take it to the מקוה mikvah again because
it might not have been to the מקוה mikvah yet. חלה ערב
פסח להיות בשבת, Chala erev Pesach lihyot b'Shabbat, let's say the 14th
was on שבת. Shabbat. Now you can't take something to the מקוה
mikvah on שבת. Shabbat. So in that case, if you wanted to
use the cleaver on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right, you would have
to have brought it to the מקוה mikvah on the 13th. So
therefore, it would be okay today. So in that case, שוחה מיד,
shocheh miyad, you can use it right away. Right, ותיקון כלי
בשבת,
vetikkun k'li
b'Shabbat, right.
בט"ו, B'tet vav, let's say you found a cleaver on the 15th
itself. So similarly, שוחה מיד, shocheh miyad, you can use it immediately
because you don't take it to the מקוה mikvah on the 15th.
You wanted it to be ready on the whoever had it wanted
to be able to use it on the 15th, so they would
have taken it the latest at the 14th. So if you find
it on the 15th, you can use it immediately. Now נמצאת קשורה
עם סכין, nimtzeit keshurah im sakkin, if a vessel is found or
the cleaver is found tied to a knife, הרי הוא כסכין, harei
hu kesakkin, whatever we assume about the knife, we assume about the
cleaver because they probably brought it to the מקוה mikvah at the
same time. So although the normal cleaver on the 14th cannot assume
to be טהור, tahor, if the cleaver and a שחיטה shechitah knife,
you know, are wrapped together and they're found on the 14th, so
the same way we assume the שחיטה shechitah knife is טהור, tahor,
we'll assume that the cleaver is טהור tahor as well.
Okay, let's move to the people walking on the road.
The assumption is that everybody is abiding by all these strictures. I
mean, what about the עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? You know, they didn't
care about...
Well, I think, oh you mean like the, well, during the normal
year it works because who, who would want to go on the
side of the road except somebody that was consciously avoiding? So during
the normal year why we say the side of the road is
okay is alright, but your question is during the רגל, regel, why
are we assuming that all of the טמאים t'meiyim people are abiding
by these types of, you know, concerns? It's true, we have to
assume that at least they care enough about communal concerns during the
רגל regel not to make life hard for other people. But you're
right, we're making that assumption.
That ties into what we do with the meat in the...
Right, actually there's an excellent article that I'm reading right now about,
I mean there's a lot of scholarship about the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz and the assumptions about them and which group of people is
it actually referring to. Anyway, so there's an article that I'm reading
about clearly about how, you know, it might have been a lesser
real group and more type of a rabbinic construct. Anyway, but that
it develops over time as well, that the idea that they both
can't be trusted with תרומה טהורה terumah t'harah and that they don't
take תרומה ומעשרות terumah u'ma'asrot were sort of at different states of
how עם הארץ am ha'aretz were conceived were those different elements added.
But it's anyway, yes, it...
So this is kind of the same idea with the meat, we
assume the majority of the people are doing it this way and
so we go with
the majority.
Right, but of course but the majority of the people aren't זבים
וזבות, zavim v'zavot, so if that was true, you'd never have to
worry about spit.
No, no, no, the majority, what I'm saying is the majority of
people are following...
Well, right, right, that's true, right. Okay, I mean, that's true, we
could sort of say if there's a few that aren't abiding by
it, you know, that that we're not going to pay attention because
still, right.
Just like with meat, what was it, 10%? 10% meat was... Right,
right.
Okay, רבי אבא בשם רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rebbi Abba b'shem Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Levi. Now, קצרן של נכרים Katzran shel nochrim היו שם.
hayu sham. Why was the שוק העליון shuk ha'elyon according to רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir considered to be the one place that's טמא? tamei?
Because
that had
a laundryman for non-Jews. Big deal. So this is assuming, like we
find out in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat and elsewhere, that חז"ל Chazal
treated non-Jews like
זב. zav. So, and and therefore a source of טומאה. tumah. So
therefore, since that was a major place for non-Jews, that's why according
to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that was, that was טמא, tamei, the
spit there was
טמא. tamei.
אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rebbi Chanina,
ארודות היו.
Arudot hayu.
Wild donkeys, right?
Rabbi Lindsay just
it's the same way in other words the חכמים chachamim treated a
corpse of a non-Jew as being a source of טומאה? tumah?
No, corpse of a non-Jew is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. No, this is a
special תקנה takkana that they wanted to in order to limit interactions
between Jews and non-Jews and they treated all non-Jews as like a
זב, zav, זב וזבות. zav v'zavos. It's a very, you know, which
obviously will make you keep your distance.
משום חתנות? mishum chasnus?
Yeah, in
general, right, general הרחקה, harchaka, right. Okay so these wild asses were
were sort of like ferreting around, how did how does the Artscroll
translate that? נוחרים nochrim
Charlie?
Oh, pilgrims.
No, no, no. ערודות היו נוחרים בירושלים. arudot hayu nochrim b'Yerushalayim. They
used to spear
them. Killing. All right. Oh, okay. All right, well that makes sense
now.
והיו עולי רגלים משתקעים בדם עד ארכובותיהם v'hayu olei regalim mishtak'im b'dam
ad arkuboteihem and people that would go up on the רגל regel
would be into you know blood up to their ankles.
בארכובסה דנחירה barkubsa d'nachira right?
Right. Wow. I thought it meant that the that the animals were
נוחרים nochrim and not that they were נוחרים nochrim the animals. Okay
that's
anyway ובאו לפני חכמים ולא אמרו להם דבר. uva'u lifnei chachamim v'lo
amru lahem davar. And they came to the sages and the sages
didn't say anything. I have no idea what this has to do
with anything. So what does it have to do with the question
about why spit being טמא tamei and whatnot? I'm not getting it
all what the context is of this. טומאה וטהרה? tumah v'taharah? What?
Maybe טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah but we're talking about spit. Anyway. All
right I do not understand what the context of this statement is.
Okay now רבי סימן בשם רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Siman b'shem
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi מעשה maaseh what? Does he say anything about
what the context is? Okay now now that we're talking about I
don't know טומאה tumah and dead donkeys we're going to talk about
the dead donkey of of the בית רבי beis rebbi and this
is word for word a סוגיא suggya that we had about two
weeks ago. So hopefully this will go fast and you'll remember this.
Okay but it's a total digression.
מעשה בפרדה של בית רבי maaseh b'pirda shel beis rebbi there was
a story in the in the donkey of Rebbe's house שמתה she-meisah
it
was it died וטיהרו דמה משום נבילה v'tihara damah mishum nevelah and
they said that the blood does not have a status of נבילה
nevelah only the meat has a status of נבילה. nevelah. Now רבי
אלעזר שאל ליה רבי סימן Rabbi Elazar sha'al lei Rabbi Siman Rabbi
Elazar asked Rabbi Siman עד כמה? ad kama? How much blood did
they say until how much was it טהור? tahor? Was the blood
categorically טהור tahor because it's not meat? Or was it only because
there was less than a certain amount and once it was a
רביעית revi'is then maybe it would be considered to be significant and
equal to a כזית k'zayis of meat and maybe it would be
טמא? tamei? So until how much blood did they say it was
טהור? tahor? ולא אגיביה v'lo agivei he didn't respond to him. שאל
ליה רבי יהושע בן לוי sha'al lei Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi so
then he went and he asked רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi אמר ליה amar lei Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said to
him עד רביעית טהור ad revi'is tahor no actually it's only טהור
tahor up to a רביעית revi'is יותר מכאן yosei mikan רביעית revi'is
and more טמא tamei it's טמא. tamei. Okay so it's not categorically
טהור. tahor. ובאש ליה רבי אלעזר דלא חזא ליה רבי סימן שמועתה
uvash lei Rabbi Elazar d'lo chaza lei Rabbi Siman shemuasoh and רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was upset it was bad in his eyes that
רבי סימן Rabbi Siman wouldn't give him an answer. No kidding. Now
we have another story about that. רבי ביבי הוה יתיב מתני הדין
עובדא Rabbi Bibi havay yasiv masnei hadein uvda Rabbi Bibi was sitting
telling over this story that they said that the blood of this
dead donkey was
טהור tahor אמר ליה רבי יצחק בר ביסנא amar lei Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Bisna so Rabbi Yitzchak bar Bisna said the question is said
to whom? So some want to say it means again said to
רבי סימן Rabbi Siman make it parallel to the previous discussion. Anyway
עד כמה? ad kama? Until until how much? אמר ליה amar lei
עד רביעית טהור יותר מכאן טמא ad revi'is tahor yosei mikan tamei
so is it until a רביעית revi'is is it טהור tahor more
than that is it טמא? tamei? Maybe that's an answer maybe it's
a question? Because we'll see the next line is ובעט ביה ubatzbei
and he kicked him. Okay so again you have one one story
that he didn't answer him another that he kicked him. So we
saw this it was before. Yeah. So
אמר ליה רבי זריקה amar lei Rabbi Zerika so רבי זריקה Rabbi
Zerika said בגין דהוה שייל לך bigin d'havay sha'il lach because he
asked you a question is it how much what's the story more
than a רביעית revi'is less than a רביעית? revi'is? And he asked
you אבעט ביה? abatzbei? He asked you a question you kick him?
That's how you respond to a question? אמר ליה amar lei בגין
דלא הוה דעתי בי bigin d'lo havay daati bi because my mind
wasn't settled דאמר רבי חנין d'amar Rabbi Chanin והיו חייך תלואים לך
מנגד v'hayu chayecha telu'im lach mineged your
your life will be suspended opposite you זה הלוקח חטים לשנה zeh
she-lokeach chittim l'shanah that you have a year's worth of grain but
nevertheless you don't you don't have a field so you don't have
the source that's going to provide for you but at least you
got a year's worth of grain stored up ופחדת לילה ויומם ufachadta
lailah v'yomam
yeah you'll be afraid day and night זה הלוקח מן הסידקי zeh
she-lokeach min hasidki
that's somebody that is buying from the provider of of grain and
therefore you don't have even have any grain but you have a
supplier ולא תאמין
בחייך
v'lo
sa'amin b'chayecha
which is even more you don't have any faith trust in your
life זה הלוקח מן הפלטר zeh she-lokeach min hapalter that's somebody that
gets from a baker which presumably is even more precarious because it
has to be baked and it's more processing and maybe even less
sense of having something on your own ואנא סמיכנא א-פלטרא v'ana samichna
a-paltera
and I rely on the פלטרא paltera so I don't know what
type of answer that is. It's actually you
know. Anyway, the whole thing was a digression because of this issue
of the donkeys, and I don't even know why we discussed the
donkeys. Maybe it was just saying that that's what they did in
this שוק shuk is that they would pierce donkeys, but then it
also,
as Dov says, it explains why it would be a place where...
and that brought more and that brought more non-Jews into the area
they would hunt this thing.
Maybe some explanation of, right, קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah says they were
killing donkeys to feed to the lions.
Yeah,
that's what the קרבן העדה Korban HaEdah says, that they were killing
the donkeys to feed to the lions. But anyway, but presumably somehow
either it's just a colorful comment to make about the שוק היווני
Shuk HaYevani or somehow as Dov says it explains why it would
be a place where טמא tamei people would go or non-Jews would
go and led to the problems we were discussing. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara goes on.
מאי
כדון?
Mai
kadon? So what is going on, meaning what's sort of like מה
הוי עלה, mah havay alah, what's the conclusion of this about the
blood of the נבלה? neveilah? So היי רבי יהושע בן בתירא על
דם נבלה שהוא טהור. Hey Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira al dam neveilah
shehu tahor. Oh, we have a משנה Mishna that says that the
blood of נבלה neveilah is טהור, tahor, categorically טהור, tahor, not based
on a just less than a minimum amount. So no, so the
answer is, if you say that it is that it will be
טמא tamei after an amount, מה טהור? mah tahor? טהור מלהכשיר. Tahor
milahachshir. It means that it won't make if that blood goes on
a fruit, it won't make it susceptible, the fruit susceptible to becoming
טמא tamei because you need a liquid to go on on food
to make it susceptible. אבל טמא מטמא. Aval tamei mitamei.
What? Blood, but not blood of נבלה, neveilah, other blood. Okay, but
to but it actually is a source of טומאה, tumah, which is
a pretty amazing read into a into a משנה Mishna that says
it's טהור tahor means that no, it is טמא. tamei. It's just
that it doesn't make other things susceptible. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't
like that answer. תמן תנינן, Tman tninan, we have another משנה, Mishna,
דם השרץ מטמא כבשרו, dam sheretz mitamei k'vesaro, the blood of a
שרץ sheretz of a rodent is טמא tamei like the flesh, you
know, with a certain amount of it causes טומאה, tumah, ומטמא ואינו
מכשיר. u'mitamei v'eino machshir. And this blood causes טומאה tumah but it
will not make food susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. ואין לנו כיוצא
בו, V'ein lanu k'yotzei bo, and no other thing is like this,
that it causes טומאה tumah of a liquid that causes טומאה tumah
but it's not מכשיר. machshir. So you can't obviously you can't say
that's the story by the נבלה, neveilah, that it's ומטמא ואינו מכשיר.
mitamei v'eino machshir. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, ואין לנו כיוצא בו כשיעור טומאתו. v'ein lanu k'yotzei bo k'shiyur
tumato. No, no, no, it means no other thing has this quality
of being ומטמא mitamei and not מכשיר machshir when the as the
שיעור shiyur of the same size, because the size of a שרץ
sheretz that it causes this is very small, כעדשה, k'adasha, like a
bean. אבל דמו מטמא כבשרו, Aval dmo mitamei k'vesaro, but we do
have other thing כשיעור, k'shiyur, but we do have other things, i.e.
a נבלה neveilah where the blood does cause טומאה. tumah. So it's
really a really very strong proofs against it, right? That it says
that we have one thing that says blood of נבלה neveilah is
טהור, tahor, we say it's only it really doesn't mean it. We
have another thing that proves that it does mean it, and the
גמרא Gemara says no, no, it just means the same quantity is
not the same. Okay, so אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosei, פליגי
בה תרי אמוראין. peligi bah try amora'in. So in the end this
is debate of two אמוראים. Amoraim. חד אמר טמא, Chad amar tamei,
one says blood of a נבלה neveilah is categorically טמא, tamei, וחד
אמר טהור, v'chad amar tahor, and the other says categorically טהור. tahor.
מן דאמר טמא Man d'amar tamei כרבי יהודה, k'Rabbi Yehuda, like רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we haven't quoted a רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but
there's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel debate about the amount, but they
both agree that blood of a נבלה neveilah is
טמא. tamei. ומן דאמר טהור U'man d'amar tahor כרבי יהושע בן בתירא,
k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira, like the משנה Mishna we quoted before, the
רבי יהושע בן בתירא Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira said the blood of
a נבלה neveilah is טהור. tahor. So even though you tried to
do a קוועטש kvetch and get out of it and say it
means it's not מכשיר, machshir, the simple sense of that משנה Mishna
is is that it is completely טהור. tahor. Okay, אמרה ליה רב
דימי דמן נחושא, amreilei Rav Dimi demin Nechusha, ויאות, v'ya'os, it actually
works out nicely. דרבי יהודה, DeRabbi Yehuda, because we said רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda the one that says that the blood of a נבלה
neveilah is טמא tamei when it's a certain amount. And he says,
מוריינא דבי נשיא הוה, moraina debei nesiah hava, he was the פוסק
posek for Rabbi's, for you know, for the נשיא's Nasi house. He
was the פוסק posek for רבי. Rabbi. So the whole story was
רבי's Rabbi donkey died and the blood they said was טהור, tahor,
and then it was said oh, only up to a certain amount,
more than a רביעית revi'it it would be טמא. tamei. And now
we're saying no some say it's starkly categorically, fine, those that say
it's starkly categorically. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it is טמא
tamei after a certain amount and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was the
פוסק posek for רבי, Rabbi, so it all works out well. Okay,
anyways that was whole deep סוגיא sugya what was digression. Let's finish
up. כל הרוקין, Kol harokin, all the spit. רקין רבי אבהו Rakin
Rabbi Abahu בשם רבי יוסי בן חנינא, beshem Rabbi Yosei ben Chanina,
לא גזרו על הרוקין שבירושלים. lo gazru al harokin shebe-Yerushalayim. Why do
we say that the spit is טמא tamei over in that marketplace,
don't we have a teaching that they did not make a that
they did not say a make a גזירה gezeirah on the spit
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that you're allowed to assume that it's טהור? tahor?
הימר לה Haimar lah רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva בשם רבי יהושע בן
לוי, beshem Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, קצין של נכרים היו שם, katzin
shel necharim hayu sham, same thing we said before just repeating it
now, no there was a wanderer for the non-Jews in that marketplace
and that was a special exception.
says it's a fortress.
A fortress, קצרן Katzran is a fortress.
That's what it says.
Okay, so the,
anyway the נושאי כלים nosei keilim here says...
to want to refer to a Roman garrison.
Garrison. Oh, maybe that would sit in, that would certainly fit in
a lot better with the whole donkey's blood and all the killing
that was going on there. That would, that would make a lot
more sense.
Okay, Artscroll says wanderer.
Yeah, well, that's what the קרבן עדה Korban Eidah says, but that
garrison makes look better. And it also makes sense maybe why they're
saying it's from, maybe they just wanted the Jews to avoid it.
Maybe it wasn't really even so much technically that the spit was
טמא, tamei, but I mean, look at, they're killing all these animals
and it's flowing with blood. It gives the Jews a reason to
avoid the whole thing. I don't know. Okay, so בשאר ימות השנה
הטמאים מהלכין שיבולת. Bish'ar yemot hashanah hatmeiyim mehalchin shibbolet. Now we've just
discussed the position of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that says it matters
the middle of the street or the edges of the street. בשאר
ימות השנה הטמאים מהלכין שיבולת Bish'ar yemot hashanah hatmeiyim mehalchin shibbolet and
the הטמאים temeiyim would go like a שיבולת, shibbolet, שיבולת. shibbolet.
I assume it means because a שיבולת shibbolet is like a, you
know, like a, what do you call it? A bundle? What? No,
is it... a stalk. Is a שיבולת shibbolet a, similar to a
sheaf?
It's a sheaf, right? Isn't it a whole sheaf? It could be
also a stalk, you got me, שיבולת שועל. shibbolet shu'al. Anyway, it's
something that is, it's something that is pretty, you know, straight and,
you know, erect. So שיבולת shibbolet means like they go like the
middle path. They go, you know, the, you know, they do the
straightaway.
והטהורים מהלכין מן הצד?
Vehattahorin mehalchin
min hatzad?
Right,
שיבולים, shibbolim, right.
So there you, so that would actually make the שיבולת shibbolet be,
not the, what, the ear of...
שיבולת לשון שביל. Shibbolet lashon shevil.
שביל? Shevil? Oh, that also works, so that even works better. Okay.
Which is the שיבולת shibbolet is שביל-like?
shevil Right, right. So that's a good question. Which is the metaphor
and which is the origin? That's a good point. Anyway, they would
go straight down the center. והטהורים מהלכין מן הצד. Vehattahorin mehalchin min
hatzad. The טהורין tahorin people would go on the edges. והטהורים מהלכין
סתם והטמאים אומרים להם פרושו. Vehattahorin mehalchin stam vehatmeiyim omrim lahem peroshu.
The טהורין tahorin would go with, not saying anything, and the הטמאים
temeiyim people in the middle, they would say, "Keep away from us,
we're טמא." tamei. ובשעת הרגל, Uvisha'at haregel, at the time of the
הרגל, Regel, הטהורים מהלכין שיבולת. hattahorin mehalchin shibbolet. The טהורין tahorin would
go in the center. והטמאים מהלכין מן הצד. Vehatmeiyim mehalchin min hatzad.
The הטמאים temeiyim people would be on the margin. הטמאים מהלכין סתם
והטהורים אומרים להם פרושו. Hatmeiyim mehalchin stam vehattahorin omrim lahem peroshu. The
הטמאים temeiyim would go without saying anything and
the טהורין tahorin would say, "Keep away." So the people that are
going in the middle are telling the people on the margins to
keep their place. Okay, stay in your place. But they're the dominant
force, the ones in the middle. Okay, כל הכלים הנמצאים. Kol hakeilim
hanimtza'im. לא כן אמר רבי אבא בשם רבי יוחנן, Lo kein amar
Rabbi Abba besheim Rabbi Yochanan, לא גזרו על הכלים שבירושלים. lo gozru
al hakeilim shebiYerushalayim. So I don't understand, what's this idea that some
of the כלים keilim are, are טמא? tamei? Don't we, according to
this idea of the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, of
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right, don't we say that there was no,
the, the, they were not גוזר? gozer? So the גמרא Gemara says,
no. מכיון שנמצאו דרך ירידה לבית הטבילה, Mikeivan shenimtzu derech yeridah leveit
hatvilah, such an obvious answer. Okay, maybe as a rule they're not
טמא. tamei. But if you find them on the way down to
the מקוה, mikvah, נעשו כהוכיח, na'asu k'hochi'ach, that's, that becomes evident. You
know, that, then it's clear what their status is. אבא שאול היה
קורא אותן ציפורין. Abba Shaul hayah korei otan tziporin. So now we're
doing a different part of the משנה. Mishnah. The vessels that were
used to, to, for grave purposes. Okay, so we spoke about three
vessels there. A basket to move bones or to move, I don't
know, to move dirt, a which is like a shovel, and a
מריצה. maritza. So what is this מריצה? maritza? So אבא שאול Abba
Shaul would call it ציפורין, tziporin, which is like, I don't know,
fingernail, maybe it was shaped something like a fingernail. מאן דאמר ציפורין
שהיה דומה לציפורין. Man d'amar tziporin shehayah domeh l'tziporin. Oh, there you
go. It was shaped like a fingernail. מאן דאמר מריצה, Man d'amar
maritza, the one that calls it מריצה maritza in our משנה, Mishnah,
שמריצה את האבן לבית הקברות. shemaritza et ha'even leveit hakevarot. It causes
the stone to run to the cemetery. So somehow it would be
used to push around stones and move them around. Okay, קופיץ, Kupitz,
now you have
the hatchet. תני, Tani, הסכין קשורה לה הרי זה כמותה. hasakin kshurah
lah harei zeh kemotah. The סכין, sakin, the knife that is tied
to it is like it. Now, that's funny because our משנה Mishnah
said, our משנה Mishnah said the opposite. Our משנה Mishnah said that
the קופיץ kupitz that's tied to the knife is like the knife.
This is saying the knife that's tied to the קופיץ kupitz is
like the קופיץ. kupitz. So this might be a ברייתא braita that
argues on the משנה. Mishnah. Others say it means that no, let's,
that it's talking about like if you have two knives together, you
know, and any one knife and you know the status of one
knife then you can assume that that's true about the status of
the other. Okay, I guess we will end here. So what's the
story, Charlie? Are we... there was a possibility...